<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.document" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Document Annotation Container</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The package <code>opennlp.tools.document</code> provides an immutable container
			that carries the original text of one document together with any number of typed
			annotation layers over it. Every annotation is anchored to a
			<code>Span</code> of the text exactly as the caller supplied it, never to a
			normalized or otherwise derived form, so any result of any pipeline step can be
			highlighted in the source text.
		</para>
		<para>
			The design follows three rules:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Offset-anchored.</emphasis> A layer is a list of
					<code>Annotation</code> values, each pairing a <code>Span</code> in original
					text coordinates with a typed value. Annotations reference other annotations
					by index within their layer, never by object identity.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Open key space.</emphasis> A layer is identified by a
					<code>LayerKey</code> that also carries the type of its values, so reading a
					layer back is statically typed. Two keys are equal when both their id and
					their value type are equal, so independently created constants for the same
					layer interoperate. The keys of the core linguistic layers live in
					<code>Layers</code>; a capability-specific layer's key lives on the annotator
					that provides it, and adding a capability never changes the container.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Immutable.</emphasis> Adding a layer returns a new
					document that shares the unchanged layers with its ancestor. Documents are
					safe to share between threads.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.pipeline">
		<title>Building a pipeline</title>
		<para>
			A pipeline step implements <code>DocumentAnnotator</code>: it reads layers from a
			document and returns a new document with its own layers added. An annotator
			declares the layers it requires and provides, and a
			<code>DocumentAnalyzer</code> validates those declarations when the pipeline is
			assembled: every required layer must be provided by an earlier annotator, and no
			two annotators may provide the same layer, so a misordered pipeline fails at
			build time rather than midway through a document.
		</para>
		<para>
			Adapters for the toolkit's own components are provided:
			<code>SentenceDetectorAnnotator</code>, <code>TokenizerAnnotator</code>,
			<code>POSTaggerAnnotator</code>, <code>NameFinderAnnotator</code>,
			<code>LemmatizerAnnotator</code>, and <code>StemmerAnnotator</code>. Each wraps
			the existing single-task API, which stays the primary API for single-task use.
			The following pipeline combines three adapters with one custom annotator and
			analyzes a two-sentence text; the components behind the adapters are any
			<code>SentenceDetector</code>, <code>Tokenizer</code>, and
			<code>POSTagger</code>, for example the ME implementations loaded from models:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
				<![CDATA[
DocumentAnalyzer analyzer = DocumentAnalyzer.builder()
    .add(new SentenceDetectorAnnotator(sentenceDetector))
    .add(new TokenizerAnnotator(tokenizer))
    .add(new POSTaggerAnnotator(tagger))
    .add(new TokenLengthAnnotator())
    .build();

Document document = analyzer.analyze("The dog barks. It naps.");]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			The resulting document carries exactly the four layers the pipeline provides.
			The sentence layer holds two annotations, <code>[0..14)</code> covering
			<code>The dog barks.</code> and <code>[15..23)</code> covering
			<code>It naps.</code>. The token layer holds five tokens whose spans refer to
			the document text even inside the second sentence, so
			<code>It</code> is <code>[15..17)</code> and <code>naps.</code> is
			<code>[18..23)</code>. Layers produced per token stay aligned with the token
			layer by position:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
				<![CDATA[
List<Annotation<String>> tokens = document.get(Layers.TOKENS);
List<Annotation<String>> tags = document.get(Layers.POS_TAGS);
for (int i = 0; i < tags.size(); i++) {
  // each tag sits on its token's span, e.g. "DT" on [0..3) for "The"
  Span span = tags.get(i).span();
}

// every span refers to the original text, so covered text round-trips
for (Annotation<String> token : tokens) {
  CharSequence covered = token.span().getCoveredText(document.text());
}]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.custom">
		<title>Writing a custom annotator</title>
		<para>
			A new capability contributes its results as one more layer without any change to
			the container. The annotator below defines its own key in its own code, reads
			the token layer, and provides one integer annotation per token; the analyzer's
			build-time validation guarantees a tokenizer ran earlier:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
				<![CDATA[
static final LayerKey<Integer> TOKEN_LENGTHS =
    LayerKey.of("token-lengths", Integer.class);

class TokenLengthAnnotator implements DocumentAnnotator {

  @Override
  public Document annotate(Document document) {
    if (document == null) {
      throw new IllegalArgumentException("document must not be null");
    }
    List<Annotation<String>> tokens = document.get(Layers.TOKENS);
    List<Annotation<Integer>> lengths = new ArrayList<>(tokens.size());
    for (Annotation<String> token : tokens) {
      lengths.add(new Annotation<>(token.span(), token.value().length()));
    }
    return document.with(TOKEN_LENGTHS, lengths);
  }

  @Override
  public Set<LayerKey<?>> requires() {
    return Set.of(Layers.TOKENS);
  }

  @Override
  public Set<LayerKey<?>> provides() {
    return Set.of(TOKEN_LENGTHS);
  }
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Reading the layer back is statically typed by the key, so the values are used as
			numbers without a cast; for the text above the five values are
			<code>3, 3, 6, 2, 5</code>, each on its token's span:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
				<![CDATA[
List<Annotation<Integer>> lengths = document.get(TOKEN_LENGTHS);
int firstTokenLength = lengths.get(0).value(); // 3, for "The" at [0..3)]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Required layers must be present, but they may be empty: an empty token layer
			yields the annotator's provided layers present but empty, so a pipeline degrades
			gracefully on documents without content. An absent required layer is rejected
			with an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> naming the layer, because a
			missing pipeline stage is an assembly error, not an empty document.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
