<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.embeddings" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Static Embeddings</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The <code>opennlp-embeddings</code> extension module produces sentence and word
			embedding vectors from a static (non-contextual) embedding table: a per-token vector
			matrix plus WordPiece tokenization. It is the modern successor to the word2vec and
			GloVe workflow. Distillation tools can compress a sentence-transformer into such a
			flat table (the Model2Vec family of releases is the primary target), and looking a
			sentence up in the table approximates the transformer's semantics at a small fraction
			of the cost: embedding a text is tokenize, gather, mean-pool, and normalize, with no
			model forward pass, no GPU, and no native runtime.
		</para>
		<para>
			Use it when embedding throughput and a pure-JVM deployment matter more than the last
			few points of retrieval quality: semantic similarity and deduplication, candidate
			retrieval for a heavier reranker, clustering, or classification features. A
			contextual model remains the better choice when distinguishing word senses in context
			is the point of the task.
		</para>
		<para>
			No model is bundled with the module. Callers point it at a model directory they
			downloaded; the table's own license applies to the table.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.api">
		<title>Embedding Text with the API</title>
		<para>
			A model directory containing <code>vocab.txt</code>, <code>model.safetensors</code>,
			<code>config.json</code>, and <code>tokenizer_config.json</code> (the layout published
			model releases use) loads with a single call; the tokenizer and pooling switches are
			read from the model's own configuration files:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
			<![CDATA[
StaticEmbeddingModel model = StaticEmbeddingModel.load(Path.of("/path/to/model-directory"));

float[] vector = model.embed("The quick brown fox");
double similarity = model.similarity("coffee", "espresso");
List<Neighbor> neighbors = model.mostSimilar("coffee", 5);
List<Neighbor> analogy = model.analogy("man", "king", "woman", 1);]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			For a model laid out differently, the explicit overload takes the two data files and
			the two switches directly: whether the tokenizer lower-cases (and strips accents),
			and whether embeddings are L2-normalized. Both are properties of the model, published
			in its configuration.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
			<![CDATA[
StaticEmbeddingModel model = StaticEmbeddingModel.load(
    Path.of("vocab.txt"), Path.of("model.safetensors"),
    true,   // lowerCase, from the model's do_lower_case
    true);  // normalize, from the model's config
]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Instances are immutable and safe for concurrent use, so one loaded model can serve
			every thread of an application. Texts with no in-vocabulary tokens embed to a zero
			vector rather than raising an error, and <code>similarity</code> reports
			<code>0</code> for them.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.safetensors">
		<title>The safetensors Reader</title>
		<para>
			Weights are read with a purpose-built reader for the safetensors format. Unlike
			pickle-based checkpoint formats, a safetensors file carries no executable content
			(the header is data-only JSON and the body is raw tensor bytes), so loading one
			cannot execute arbitrary code. Only the header is read eagerly; tensor data streams
			directly into the decoded array, so the file size is not limited by Java's
			int-indexed arrays. One decoded tensor is capped at the maximum Java array length
			(about 2.1 billion float elements), checked explicitly.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
