<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.embeddings" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Static Embeddings</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The <code>opennlp-embeddings</code> extension module produces sentence and word
			embedding vectors from a static (non-contextual) embedding table: a per-token vector
			matrix plus subword tokenization, WordPiece or SentencePiece. It is the modern
			successor to the word2vec and GloVe workflow. Distillation tools can compress a
			sentence-transformer into such a flat table (the Model2Vec family of releases is the
			primary target), and looking a sentence up in the table approximates the transformer's
			semantics at a small fraction of the cost: embedding a text is tokenize, gather,
			mean-pool, and normalize, with no model forward pass, no GPU, and no native runtime.
			SentencePiece support covers multilingual tables distilled from encoders of the
			XLM-RoBERTa family, whose vectors embed different languages into the same space.
		</para>
		<para>
			Use it when embedding throughput and a pure-JVM deployment matter more than the last
			few points of retrieval quality: semantic similarity and deduplication, candidate
			retrieval for a heavier reranker, clustering, or classification features. A
			contextual model remains the better choice when distinguishing word senses in context
			is the point of the task.
		</para>
		<para>
			OpenNLP supports contextual, ONNX-backed sentence vectors as well, in the
			<code>opennlp-dl</code> module. Those are inherently more accurate; Model2Vec trades
			some accuracy for a large speed gain. Both paths implement the same
			<code>TextEmbedder</code> interface (in <code>opennlp-api</code>), so an application can
			swap one for the other without changing its calling code.
		</para>
		<para>
			No model is bundled with the module. Callers point it at a model directory they
			downloaded; the table's own license applies to the table.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.api">
		<title>Embedding Text with the API</title>
		<para>
			A model directory loads with a single call, and the tokenizer family is detected from
			the files present. A WordPiece model carries <code>vocab.txt</code>,
			<code>model.safetensors</code>, <code>config.json</code>, and
			<code>tokenizer_config.json</code>; a SentencePiece model carries a trained
			<code>.model</code> file (<code>sentencepiece.bpe.model</code>,
			<code>spiece.model</code>, or <code>tokenizer.model</code>) next to
			<code>tokenizer.json</code>, <code>model.safetensors</code>, and
			<code>config.json</code>. The tokenizer and pooling switches are read from the model's
			own configuration files:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
			<![CDATA[
StaticEmbeddingModel model = StaticEmbeddingModel.load(Path.of("/path/to/model-directory"));

float[] vector = model.embed("The quick brown fox");
double similarity = model.similarity("coffee", "espresso");
List<Neighbor> neighbors = model.mostSimilar("coffee", 5);
List<Neighbor> analogy = model.analogy("man", "king", "woman", 1);]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			<code>StaticEmbeddingUsageExampleTest</code> asserts the load-and-query workflow
			shown here.
		</para>
		<para>
			For a model laid out differently, the explicit overloads take the data files and the
			switches directly. The WordPiece overload takes whether the tokenizer lower-cases
			(and strips accents) and whether embeddings are L2-normalized; both are properties of
			the model, published in its configuration. The SentencePiece overload has no casing
			switch, because the trained <code>.model</code> file carries the model's own text
			normalizer.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
			<![CDATA[
StaticEmbeddingModel model = StaticEmbeddingModel.load(
    Path.of("vocab.txt"), Path.of("model.safetensors"),
    StaticEmbeddingModel.Casing.UNCASED,      // from the model's do_lower_case
    StaticEmbeddingModel.Normalization.L2);   // from the model's config

StaticEmbeddingModel multilingual = StaticEmbeddingModel.loadSentencePiece(
    Path.of("sentencepiece.bpe.model"), Path.of("tokenizer.json"),
    Path.of("model.safetensors"),
    StaticEmbeddingModel.Normalization.L2);
]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Matrix rows are resolved by piece string, never by tokenizer id, because the two
			files of a SentencePiece model routinely order and offset their ids differently. A
			poolable piece with no matrix row fails loud at load time. Distillation output
			usually ships without the trained <code>.model</code> file; copy that one file from
			the teacher model's own repository into the model directory, and the loader names
			exactly this fix if the file is missing.
		</para>
		<para>
			Instances are immutable and safe for concurrent use, so one loaded model can serve
			every thread of an application. Texts with no in-vocabulary tokens embed to a zero
			vector rather than raising an error (matching the reference implementation), and
			<code>similarity</code> reports <code>0</code> for them. This is a rare edge case for
			text in the model's language, since subword tokenization backs off to smaller pieces;
			it mostly happens for empty input or text outside the vocabulary's coverage.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.embeddings.safetensors">
		<title>The safetensors Reader</title>
		<para>
			Weights are read with a purpose-built reader for the safetensors format. Unlike
			pickle-based checkpoint formats, a safetensors file carries no executable content
			(the header is data-only JSON and the body is raw tensor bytes), so loading one
			cannot execute arbitrary code. Only the header is read eagerly; tensor data streams
			directly into the decoded array, so the file size is not limited by Java's
			int-indexed arrays. One decoded tensor is capped at the maximum Java array length
			(about 2.1 billion float elements), checked explicitly.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
