<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.geo">

	<title>Gazetteers and Geocoding</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
			A gazetteer maps place names to place records. The
			<code>opennlp.tools.geo.Gazetteer</code> interface is the one seam every
			lookup goes through: a bundled table, a downloaded dataset, an ingested
			database, and a remote service client are all implementations of this
			one interface, and any of them can be handed to the components that
			consume it. Each record is a <code>GazetteerEntry</code> carrying the
			canonical and alternate names, a point location, an optional bounding
			box, the ISO 3166-1 country code, a coarse feature class, the
			population, and dataset-specific extras as provenance-tagged
			attributes.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <code>opennlp-geo</code> module ships three file-backed
			implementations: <code>BundledGazetteer</code> over the bundled Natural
			Earth populated-places table, <code>GeoNamesGazetteer</code> over a
			user-downloaded GeoNames extract, and <code>OvertureGazetteer</code>
			over an Overture divisions export. All implementations are immutable
			and thread-safe after loading, so one instance can be shared across
			threads.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.user">
		<title>User-supplied places</title>
		<para>
			<code>UserGazetteer</code> loads places a public dataset does not know,
			for example customer sites or internal facility names, from a
			user-authored file, so they take part in geocoding and everything
			downstream of it. The file holds one place per line with tab-separated
			columns in this order, where trailing columns may be omitted and an
			empty column means absent: record id, canonical name, alternate names
			separated by <code>|</code>, latitude, longitude, country code, feature
			class, population, bounding box as
			<code>west,south,east,north</code>, containment chain separated by
			<code>|</code>, and one <code>key=value</code> attribute per further
			column. Lines starting with <code>#</code> and blank lines are
			skipped.
		</para>
		<para>
			A row needs either both coordinates or a bounding box; with only a
			bounding box the point location becomes the box's center. Free-text
			metadata such as a postal address belongs in an attribute column: it is
			carried verbatim on the entry and is never parsed or matched. The
			following file, whose columns are separated by single tab characters,
			defines a plant with an address attribute and a campus located through
			its bounding box alone.
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
# id	name	alternates	lat	lon	cc	class	pop	bbox	containment	attributes
plant-3	Acme Plant 3	Plant 3|The Plant	33.75	-84.39	US	POI	0		Georgia|Fulton County	address=123 Main St, Atlanta GA 30303
campus-east	Acme Campus East				US	POI	0	-84.5,33.6,-84.2,33.9]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.overlay">
		<title>Overlaying a base gazetteer</title>
		<para>
			<code>OverlayGazetteer</code> composes a base gazetteer with
			user-supplied changes: additions from a second gazetteer, and
			suppression rules hiding base entries. Consumers see one merged view
			through the same <code>Gazetteer</code> interface, so every component
			downstream picks the changes up without knowing they exist. Additions
			rank first in lookups. Suppressions hide entries of the base only,
			never additions, so a rule plus an addition with the same name replaces
			a base entry.
		</para>
		<para>
			A suppression rule is a place name with optional country and
			feature-class filters, one rule per line with tab-separated columns.
			The following file removes the city of Mobile, Alabama, from a corpus
			where that reading is always noise, while leaving every other
			<code>Mobile</code>-named record intact.
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
# name	country	feature class
Mobile	US	CITY]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The composed gazetteer then answers lookups from both sides: the
			customer file wins for its own names, and the suppressed city is gone
			from every query.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
Gazetteer base = BundledGazetteer.getInstance();
Gazetteer customer = UserGazetteer.load(Path.of("customer_places.txt"), "customer");
List<Suppression> rules = UserGazetteer.loadSuppressions(Path.of("suppress.txt"));
Gazetteer gazetteer = new OverlayGazetteer(base, customer, rules);

GazetteerEntry plant = gazetteer.lookup("Plant 3").get(0);
// plant.name() = "Acme Plant 3", plant.source() = "customer"
// plant.attributes().get("address").value() = "123 Main St, Atlanta GA 30303"

gazetteer.lookup("Mobile");    // empty: the Alabama city is suppressed
gazetteer.lookup("Tokyo");     // unaffected base entries stay visible]]>
			</programlisting>
			The additions side does not have to be a file: any
			<code>Gazetteer</code> implementation serves, so entries ingested from
			a database or fetched from a service compose the same way.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
