<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<chapter id="opennlp.ml">
<title>Machine Learning</title>
	<section id="opennlp.ml.maxent">
		<title>Maximum Entropy</title>
		<para>
		To explain what maximum entropy is, it will be simplest to quote from Manning and Schutze* (p. 589):
		<quote>
		Maximum entropy modeling is a framework for integrating information from many heterogeneous
		information sources for classification.  The data for a  classification problem is described
		as a (potentially large) number of features.  These features can be quite complex and allow
		the experimenter to make use of prior knowledge about what types of informations are expected
		to be important for classification. Each feature corresponds to a constraint on the model.
		We then compute the maximum entropy model, the model with the maximum entropy of all the models
		that satisfy the constraints.  This term may seem perverse, since we have spent most of the book
		trying to minimize the (cross) entropy of models, but the idea is that we do not want to go beyond
		the data.  If we chose a model with less entropy, we would add `information' constraints to the
		model that are not justified by the empirical evidence available to us. Choosing the maximum
		entropy model is motivated by the desire to preserve as much uncertainty as possible.
		</quote>
		</para>
		<para>
		So that gives a rough idea of what the maximum entropy framework is.
		Don't assume anything about your probability distribution other than what you have observed. 
		</para>
		<para>
		On the engineering level, using maxent is an excellent way of creating programs which perform
		very difficult classification tasks very well.  For example,  precision and recall figures for
		programs using maxent models have reached (or are) the state of the art on tasks like part of
		speech tagging, sentence detection, prepositional phrase attachment, and named entity recognition.
		On the engineering level, an added benefit is that the person creating a maxent model only needs
		to inform the training procedure of the event space, and need not worry about independence between
		features.
		</para>
		<para>
		While the authors of this implementation of maximum entropy are generally interested using
		maxent models in natural language processing, the framework is certainly quite general and
		useful for a much wider variety of fields.  In fact, maximum entropy modeling was originally
		developed for statistical physics.
		</para>
		<para>
		For a very in-depth discussion of how maxent can be used in natural language processing,
		try reading Adwait Ratnaparkhi's dissertation.   Also,  check out Berger, Della Pietra,
		and Della Pietra's paper A Maximum Entropy Approach to Natural Language Processing, which
		provides an excellent introduction and discussion of the framework.
		</para>
		<para>
		*Foundations of statistical natural language processing . Christopher D. Manning, Hinrich Schutze. 
		Cambridge, Mass. : MIT Press, c1999.
		</para>
			<section id="opennlp.ml.maxent.impl">
		<title>Implementation</title>
		<para>
		We have tried to make the opennlp.maxent implementation easy to use.  To create a model, one
		needs (of course) the training data, and then implementations of two interfaces in the
		opennlp.maxent package, EventStream and ContextGenerator.  These have fairly simple specifications,
		and example implementations can be found in the OpenNLP Tools preprocessing components.
		</para>
		<para>
		We have also set in place some interfaces and code to make it easier to automate the training
		and evaluation process (the Evalable interface and the TrainEval class).  It is not necessary
		to use this functionality, but if you do you'll find it much easier to see how well your models
		are doing.  The opennlp.grok.preprocess.namefind package is an example of a maximum entropy
		component which uses this functionality.
		</para>
		<para>
		We have managed to use several techniques to reduce the size of the models when writing them to
		disk, which also means that reading in a model for use is much quicker than with less compact
		encodings of the model.  This was especially important to us since we use many maxent models in
		the Grok library, and we wanted the start up time and the physical size of the library to be as
		minimal as possible. As of version 1.2.0, maxent has an io package which greatly simplifies the
		process of loading and saving models in different formats.
		</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>