<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.normalizer" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Text Normalization</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The package <code>opennlp.tools.util.normalizer</code> provides Unicode-aware text
			normalization for matching, search, and tokenization preprocessing. It cleans up the
			kinds of inconsistency that real text carries when it is copied from the web, PDFs,
			office documents, or multilingual sources: spacing that is not an ordinary space, the
			many dash and quotation variants, decomposed versus precomposed accents, non-ASCII
			digits, and invisible control characters.
		</para>
		<para>
			The implementation follows three principles:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Standards-sourced.</emphasis> Membership sets come from the
					Unicode Character Database (for example the <code>White_Space</code> and
					<code>Dash</code> properties), not from the JVM's locale-dependent or quirky
					character predicates. The normalization engine never relies on
					<code>Character.isWhitespace</code>, which disagrees with the Unicode standard.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Cursor-based, no regular expressions.</emphasis> Every
					operation is a single forward pass over the input that tests membership in O(1)
					and advances by code point. This avoids the allocation and the catastrophic
					backtracking (ReDoS) risk of regular expressions, and it correctly recognizes
					Unicode characters that Java's <code>\s</code> does not.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Offset-preserving.</emphasis> The original text is always
					the source of truth. Normalization produces a derived form for matching while the
					original character offsets are kept, so a search hit can be reported and
					highlighted against the source even when the normalized form has a different
					length.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Two engines underpin everything: the <code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code> family offers
			ready-made, composable normalizers, and the <code>CharClass</code> engine is the low-level,
			configurable building block they are made of. Built on these are four higher-level
			features documented below: a layered term model that projects a token through a
			configurable stack of transforms while keeping every intermediate form (see
			<xref linkend="tools.normalizer.term"/>), an opt-in emoji annotation layer that turns
			pictographs into typed signal (see <xref linkend="tools.normalizer.emojiannotations"/>),
			per-language profiles that select the transforms
			appropriate to a language (see <xref linkend="tools.normalizer.language"/>), and confusable
			folding that reduces lookalike characters for matching (see
			<xref linkend="tools.normalizer.confusables"/>).
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.normalizers">
		<title>The normalizer family</title>
		<para>
			Each normalizer implements the existing
			<code>opennlp.tools.util.normalizer.CharSequenceNormalizer</code> interface
			(<code>CharSequence normalize(CharSequence)</code>) and is, by default, a shared stateless instance
			obtained through <code>getInstance()</code> (case and accent folding also offer
			configured forms). They can therefore be combined with the
			existing <code>AggregateCharSequenceNormalizer</code>, or with the
			<code>TextNormalizer</code> builder described below.
		</para>

		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Normalizer</entry>
						<entry>Effect</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><code>WhitespaceCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Collapses each run of Unicode whitespace to a single ASCII space and
							trims the edges.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>LineBreakPreservingWhitespaceCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Collapses horizontal whitespace runs to a single ASCII space but keeps a
							run containing a line break as a single newline, so paragraph structure
							survives; trims the edges.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>DashCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Maps every Unicode dash to the ASCII hyphen-minus. The mathematical
							minus signs and the soft hyphen are not affected.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>QuoteCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Folds typographic single quotes and apostrophes to <code>'</code> and
							double quotes (including guillemets) to <code>"</code>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>DigitCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Maps Unicode decimal digits (Arabic-Indic, Devanagari, fullwidth, ...)
							to ASCII <code>0</code>-<code>9</code> by their numeric value.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>EllipsisCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Expands the horizontal ellipsis to <code>...</code> and the two-dot
							leader to <code>..</code></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>BulletCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Replaces unambiguous list bullets with a space; the Catalan middle dot
							is left alone.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>InvisibleCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Removes invisible format and bidirectional control characters (BOM,
							zero width space, bidi marks/overrides/isolates, ...). The zero width
							joiner and non-joiner and variation selectors are kept.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>NfcCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Applies Unicode Normalization Form C (canonical composition); a safe,
							lossless baseline for matching.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>NfkcCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Applies Unicode Normalization Form KC (compatibility composition);
							folds fullwidth forms, ligatures, and super/subscripts.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>CaseFoldCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Lower cases for case-insensitive matching, using
							<code>Locale.ROOT</code>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>AccentFoldCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Folds diacritics in a script-aware way (see below).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>GermanUmlautCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Transliterates German umlauts and the eszett (a-umlaut to <code>ae</code>,
							eszett to <code>ss</code>; DIN 5007-2).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>ConfusableSkeletonCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Reduces lookalike characters to a confusable skeleton for matching
							(UTS #39); see below.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>EmojiToEmoticonCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Folds emoji to ASCII emoticons from a bundled project-authored mapping
							(U+1F642 to <code>:)</code>); an emoji presentation sequence (a pictograph
							followed by U+FE0F) folds as one unit. Unmapped content passes through.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><code>EmoticonToEmojiCharSequenceNormalizer</code></entry>
						<entry>Folds an ASCII emoticon that stands alone between whitespace to its
							pictograph (<code>:-)</code> to U+1F642). An embedded sequence, such as the
							<code>:/</code> in <code>https://</code>, is left alone. Applied before
							tokenization, it lets emoticons survive as single emoji tokens.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>

		<para>
			A single normalizer is applied directly:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharSequenceNormalizer ws = WhitespaceCharSequenceNormalizer.getInstance();
String clean = ws.normalize("a 　b").toString();   // "a b"

String hyphen = DashCharSequenceNormalizer.getInstance()
    .normalize("state—of–the‐art").toString(); // "state-of-the-art"]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.pipeline">
		<title>Composing a pipeline</title>
		<para>
			<code>TextNormalizer</code> is a fluent builder that composes the rungs, in the order
			they are added, into a single <code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code>:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharSequenceNormalizer pipeline = TextNormalizer.builder()
    .nfc()
    .caseFold()
    .accentFold()
    .build();

String term = pipeline.normalize("CAFÉ").toString();   // "cafe"]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			A conservative search-oriented chain (strip invisibles, NFC, collapse whitespace, fold
			quotes and dashes, case fold, then script-gated accent fold) is available directly:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharSequenceNormalizer chain = TextNormalizer.defaultChain();

// byte order mark stripped, curly quotes folded, case and accent folded
String t = chain.normalize("﻿“CafÉ”").toString();   // "\"cafe\""]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Any custom <code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code> can be inserted with
			<code>with(...)</code>. The <code>TextNormalizer</code> pipeline and the individual
			<code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code> implementations are not applied automatically by
			statistical OpenNLP components; callers compose them explicitly when preprocessing text
			for search or matching; to recover original character offsets from the composed result,
			see <xref linkend="tools.normalizer.aligned"/>. The DL components described in
			<xref linkend="tools.normalizer.dl"/> use a narrower, built-in subset of this machinery.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.aligned">
		<title>Offset-aware pipelines</title>
		<para>
			<code>build()</code> returns a normalizer that yields only the cleaned text. When you also
			need to map a match found in the normalized text back to the original (to highlight a search
			hit in the source, say), build the pipeline with <code>buildAligned()</code> instead. It
			returns an <code>OffsetAwareNormalizer</code> whose <code>normalizeAligned(text)</code> returns
			an <code>AlignedText</code>: the normalized string together with an <code>Alignment</code> that
			maps spans between the two forms, composed across every stage, so a match maps straight back to
			the source even when a stage collapsed a run or folded a multi-unit character.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[OffsetAwareNormalizer pipeline = TextNormalizer.builder()
    .whitespace()      // collapses runs, so it changes length and shifts offsets
    .dashes()
    .buildAligned();

String original = "find   the—match";
AlignedText aligned = pipeline.normalizeAligned(original);
// aligned.normalized()                ->  "find the-match"
Span hit = aligned.toOriginalSpan(5, 14);   // "the-match" in the normalized text
// hit.getCoveredText(original)         ->  "the—match"   (back to the source, em dash and all)]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			<code>OffsetAwareNormalizer</code> is a capability interface: it extends
			<code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code> and adds <code>normalizeAligned</code>, so a caller tests
			for it with a plain <code>instanceof</code>, the same pattern the name finder uses for
			<code>OffsetMappingNameFinder</code>. Every per-code-point fold implements it: whitespace, the
			line-break-preserving whitespace rung, dashes, invisible-control stripping, quotes, digits,
			ellipsis, bullets, the German umlaut transliteration, Unicode full case folding
			(<code>fullCaseFold()</code>, whose expansions come from a bundled table with known lengths,
			so it reports its edits), and the emoji/emoticon folds (<code>emojiToEmoticon()</code> and
			<code>emoticonToEmoji()</code>, backed by the same kind of known-length bundled table). The
			folds that route through
			<code>java.text.Normalizer</code> (NFC, NFKC, accent folding, and confusable folding) or
			through JDK case mapping (the locale-based <code>caseFold()</code>) cannot report their
			per-character edits, so they do not implement the interface, and a chain that contains one
			is rejected by <code>buildAligned()</code> with an <code>IllegalStateException</code> that
			names the step, rather than returning a pipeline that would hand back an offset that does
			not hold. The per-stage maps and their composition use the <code>Alignment</code> machinery
			described in <xref linkend="tools.normalizer.charclass"/>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.dl">
		<title>Use in DL components</title>
		<para>
			<code>NameFinderDL</code> and <code>DocumentCategorizerDL</code> share Unicode-aware text
			handling through <code>AbstractDL</code>. Long inputs are split into overlapping chunks
			on the full Unicode <code>White_Space</code> set (no-break space, ideographic space, line
			and paragraph separators, and the other members listed under
			<xref linkend="tools.normalizer.reference"/>), not on Java's six-character
			<code>\s</code> subset. Empty tokens from leading, trailing, or repeated whitespace are
			not produced.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>NameFinderDL</code> additionally locates reconstructed entity text in the original
			input with a cursor-based matcher: a space in the reconstructed span matches zero or more
			Unicode whitespace code points in the source, and every other code point is compared
			case-insensitively. This replaces the previous regular-expression approach and correctly
			handles spacing copied from PDFs, the web, or non-Latin sources when resolving
			<code>Span#getCoveredText(...)</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Optional input folding is controlled through <code>InferenceOptions</code> and is
			<emphasis>off by default</emphasis> so existing models keep their prior inputs unless
			you opt in:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>setNormalizeWhitespace(true)</code> maps each Unicode whitespace code point
					to a single ASCII space before inference. The transform is one code point to one
					space, so character offsets stay aligned with the input.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>setNormalizeDashes(true)</code> maps each dash in the default
					<code>CharClass.dashes()</code> set to the ASCII hyphen-minus. Mathematical minus
					signs and the soft hyphen are not affected unless you extend the set explicitly.
					This replacement is also one code point to one character for Basic Multilingual
					Plane dashes. A dash in the supplementary planes shrinks from two UTF-16 units
					to one, which shifts later offsets, so with this fold enabled <code>find</code>
					reports offsets into the normalized text in that case while
					<code>findInOriginal</code> maps them back to the original input.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Run-collapsing normalization (for example <code>WhitespaceCharSequenceNormalizer</code>,
			which collapses whitespace <emphasis>runs</emphasis> to a single space) is not enabled
			through these flags because it would shift character offsets. Use the
			<code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code> pipeline directly when you need that behavior on text
			that does not require offset-preserving span lookup. See also
			<xref linkend="tools.namefind.api.onnx"/> and
			<xref linkend="tools.doccat.api.onnx"/>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[InferenceOptions options = new InferenceOptions();
options.setNormalizeWhitespace(true);   // opt-in: NBSP, ideographic space, ... -> ASCII space
options.setNormalizeDashes(true);       // opt-in: en dash, em dash, ... -> hyphen-minus

NameFinderDL finder = new NameFinderDL(model, vocab, ids2Labels, options, sentenceDetector);]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.accentfold">
		<title>Diacritic folding and multilingual safety</title>
		<para>
			<code>AccentFoldCharSequenceNormalizer</code> folds accents for search, but does so in a
			script-aware way that a Latin-only folding filter cannot. It decomposes the text, then
			drops nonspacing combining marks only for base characters whose script is configured for
			folding (Latin, Greek, and Cyrillic by default). Combining marks on other scripts are
			left untouched, because there they are essential orthography rather than decoration:
			dropping an Indic vowel sign or virama, an Arabic harakat, a Hebrew point, or a Thai
			vowel would change the word.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharSequenceNormalizer fold = AccentFoldCharSequenceNormalizer.getInstance();

fold.normalize("café");                 // "cafe"   (Latin accent folded)
fold.normalize("ά");                    // "α" (Greek alpha-with-tonos -> alpha)
fold.normalize("का");              // unchanged (Devanagari is left intact)]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Atomic Latin letters that do not decompose are mapped to an ASCII approximation by
			default: for example the stroke letters and ligatures, eszett, and thorn
			(<code>ø -&gt; o</code>, <code>æ -&gt; ae</code>, <code>ß -&gt; ss</code>,
			<code>þ -&gt; th</code>). Both behaviors are configurable through the constructor:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[// fold only Latin, and do not map the stroke letters
CharSequenceNormalizer latinOnly = new AccentFoldCharSequenceNormalizer(
    java.util.Set.of(Character.UnicodeScript.LATIN), false);]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Diacritic folding is a recall optimization, not a linguistically correct transform, so it
			is intended for a search or matching form rather than for display. Language-specific case
			and letter rules (for example German <code>DIN</code> umlaut expansion, or the Turkish
			dotless-i) are out of scope for the default folder and should be applied with an explicit
			locale upstream.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.charclass">
		<title>The CharClass engine and code point sets</title>
		<para>
			The set-based normalizers are built on <code>CharClass</code>, a configurable class of
			Unicode code points paired with a single canonical replacement, backed by a
			<code>CodePointSet</code> with O(1) membership. You choose both the membership and the
			replacement code point with <code>CharClass.of(members, replacement)</code>; whitespace and
			dashes are the two built-in presets, and any other class is one more configured instance:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharClass ws = CharClass.whitespace();   // Unicode White_Space -> U+0020
CharClass dash = CharClass.dashes();      // Unicode Dash (curated) -> U+002D

ws.collapse("a   b");                      // "a b"          (runs -> one space)
ws.trim("  hi  ");                         // "hi"
String[] tokens = ws.split("one two"); // ["one", "two"]  (offset-aware via splitSpans)
dash.normalize("a—b");                // "a-b"]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			A class applies its replacement three ways, which differ in whether they collapse runs and
			whether they preserve character offsets:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>normalize(text)</code> replaces each member one-for-one with the replacement,
					so it is length- and offset-preserving; use it when you still need spans back into
					the original text.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>collapse(text)</code> reduces each maximal run of members to a single
					replacement; it changes length, so it is a search and match transform.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>collapsePreserving(text, keep, keepReplacement)</code> collapses runs but emits
					<code>keepReplacement</code> for any run containing a kept code point, which is how
					you squish horizontal whitespace while keeping line breaks.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			So the replacement is your choice and the method picks the behavior. Folding tabs and
			newlines to a single newline, for example, is one configured class:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CharClass lineFold = CharClass.of(CodePointSet.of('\n', '\t'), '\n');
lineFold.collapse("\n\n\n\t\n");   // "\n"  (the whole run folds to one newline)

CharClass ws = CharClass.whitespace();
ws.collapsePreserving(text, CodePointSet.of('\n'), '\n');   // squish spaces, keep paragraph breaks]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			When you need the normalized form together with a map back to the original, the
			<code>normalizeAligned</code>, <code>collapseAligned</code>,
			<code>collapsePreservingAligned</code>, <code>trimAligned</code>, and
			<code>removeAllAligned</code> variants return an <code>AlignedText</code> that carries an
			<code>Alignment</code>. The alignment maps spans between the two forms with
			<code>toOriginalSpan</code> and <code>toNormalizedSpan</code>, staying correct across
			deletions and length-changing folds, and composes with <code>andThen</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			A <code>CodePointSet</code> can be built explicitly, as a range, by union, or loaded from
			a user definitions file so that delimiters can be extended without a code change. The
			file is line oriented and parsed with the same cursor approach (no regular expression): a
			<code>[name]</code> line opens a section, a <code>#</code> begins a comment, and each
			remaining line is a hex code point or an inclusive range.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="none">
<![CDATA[[whitespace]
U+00A0          # no-break space
U+2000-U+200A   # typographic spaces

[dash]
U+2E5D          # oblique hyphen]]>
		</programlisting>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[CodePointSet extra = CodePointSet.fromFile(path, "whitespace");
CharClass wsPlus = CharClass.whitespace().withAdditional(extra);]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.term">
		<title>The layered term model</title>
		<para>
			<code>TermAnalyzer</code> tokenizes text and gives each token a
			<emphasis>stack</emphasis> of normalization layers while keeping its source span. It is the
			offset-preserving entry point for matching: the normalized form is
			what you index or query, and the span ties every layer back to the original text for
			highlighting, even when normalization changes a token's length. A <code>Term</code> is one
			token projected through an ordered chain of
			<code>Dimension</code>s: original, NFC, NFKC, whitespace, dash, case fold, full case fold, accent fold,
			emoji fold, confusable fold, stem, and lemma. The order is fixed because the transforms do not commute
			(case folding then accent folding differs from the reverse). The original is always kept,
			so aggressive folding stays safe and a match on any layer maps back to the source through
			the token's <code>Span</code>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[TermAnalyzer analyzer = TermAnalyzer.builder()
    .caseFold()
    .stem(new PorterStemmer())
    .build();

Term term = analyzer.analyze("Running").get(0);
// term.original()           -> "Running"
// term.normalized()         -> "run"      (the final configured dimension, here STEM)
// term.peel()               -> "running"  (the layer below the top, O(1))
// term.at(Dimension.NFC)    -> computed lazily on first request, then cached]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Segmentation uses the <xref linkend="tools.tokenizer.uax29"/> word tokenizer, so the input
			does not need to be pre-tokenized. The dimensions named in the builder are computed eagerly;
			any other dimension is computed on first request, applied on top of the final form, and
			cached, so querying a configured layer or peeling the last one is O(1) and adding an
			unrequested dimension costs one transform. The character-level dimensions have built-in
			defaults; <code>STEM</code> and <code>LEMMA</code> require a
			<code>Stemmer</code> or <code>Lemmatizer</code> (and <code>LEMMA</code> a part-of-speech
			tag), and fail loudly if requested without them. An analyzer configured with a stemmer is
			not thread-safe, because the Snowball stemmers are stateful.
		</para>
		<para>
			Each dimension's transform is configurable on the builder. Beyond the no-argument methods
			that enable a dimension with its default, there are convenience methods for the common
			knobs, and a general <code>transform(dimension, normalizer)</code> escape hatch for any
			character-level dimension:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[TermAnalyzer analyzer = TermAnalyzer.builder()
    .whitespace(CharClass.of(CodePointSet.of('\n', '\t'), '\n')::collapse) // custom target/behavior
    .caseFold(Locale.forLanguageTag("tr"))                                 // Turkish case rules
    .accentFold(Set.of(Character.UnicodeScript.LATIN), false)              // fold only Latin
    .maxTokenLength(255)                                                   // tokenizer chopping
    .build();]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			The whitespace and dash methods take any <code>CharSequenceNormalizer</code>, so a
			<code>CharClass</code> method reference (<code>::normalize</code> for one-for-one,
			<code>::collapse</code> for run-collapsing) selects both the fold target and the behavior.
			The case-fold method takes a <code>Locale</code> for language-specific rules such as the
			Turkish dotted/dotless i, and the accent-fold method takes the scripts to fold and whether
			to fold stroke letters.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.emojiannotations">
		<title>Emoji annotations</title>
		<para>
			Beyond folding, a pictograph carries signal worth keeping: a name, a coarse sentiment, an
			entity type, a document category, and for flags a region. <code>EmojiAnnotator</code> is the
			opt-in surface for that signal. It assembles one <code>EmojiAnnotation</code> record per
			symbol from three strictly separated layers: <emphasis>bundled facts</emphasis> from the
			provenance-tagged, project-authored <code>emoji-annotations.txt</code> table,
			<emphasis>derived facts</emphasis> computed from the code point sequence itself
			(<code>EmojiFlags</code> decodes a regional indicator pair to its ISO 3166-1 alpha-2 code and
			a subdivision tag sequence to its ISO 3166-2 code, with no data file), and optional
			<emphasis>joined facts</emphasis> resolved at run time through an
			<code>EmojiAnnotationJoin</code> hook against user-installed data such as a gazetteer.
			Every attribute value carries its own provenance source, and gazetteer identifiers are never
			baked into the bundled table.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[EmojiAnnotator annotator = new EmojiAnnotator();
TermAnalyzer analyzer = TermAnalyzer.builder().emojiFold().build();

// "Berlin <German flag> <red heart>"
String text = "Berlin \uD83C\uDDE9\uD83C\uDDEA \u2764\uFE0F";
for (Term term : analyzer.analyze(text)) {
  annotator.annotate(term).ifPresent(a -> {
    a.name();        // "red heart" for the heart (CLDR short name)
    a.sentiment();   // 2 for the heart (project-authored coarse score, -2..2)
    a.entityType();  // FLAG for the flag, HEART for the heart
    a.category();    // FLAGS / SMILEYS_AND_EMOTION
    a.isoRegion();   // "DE" for the flag, decoded from the sequence itself
  });
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			<code>EmojiAnnotatorUsageExampleTest</code> asserts the behavior shown here.
			Annotations are per-symbol <emphasis>metadata</emphasis>, not text transforms, so they are a
			parallel accessor surface beside <code>Term</code> rather than additional
			<code>Dimension</code>s: <code>annotate(Term)</code> reads the token's original layer, which
			is the symbol the author actually wrote even after a fold dimension has rewritten it to
			ASCII. Annotation is total over arbitrary tokens (a non-emoji token is simply empty, and
			degenerate flag-shaped text yields no region instead of an exception), while the strict
			decoder <code>EmojiFlags.isoRegion()</code> fails loudly on malformed sequences for callers
			that want the contract. The bundled table's sentiment scores are original project judgments
			(tagged <code>UNSPECIFIED</code>); its names and its entity-type/category assignments derive
			from the Unicode-licensed CLDR short names and <code>emoji-test.txt</code> group headers, and
			no third-party sentiment data set is included.
		</para>
		<para>
			The annotations are wired as strictly opt-in feature inputs to three components, each
			through its existing extension seam so that default behavior and existing models are
			unchanged: the name finder (and any consumer of feature generation descriptors) activates
			<code>EmojiAnnotationFeatureGenerator</code> by naming
			<code>EmojiAnnotationFeatureGeneratorFactory</code> in a descriptor, the document
			categorizer takes <code>EmojiFeatureGenerator</code> alongside its defaults through the
			<code>DoccatFactory</code> feature generator array, and sentiment analysis trains with
			<code>EmojiSentimentFactory</code>, whose context generator adds the emoji evidence and is
			re-created from the model manifest at prediction time. A flag token then carries
			gazetteer-like evidence (<code>emoji.type=FLAG</code>, <code>emoji.region=DE</code>) with no
			dictionary, and a heart or crying face contributes its coarse polarity directly.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.confusables">
		<title>Confusable (homoglyph) folding</title>
		<para>
			<code>Confusables</code> reduces text to its Unicode confusable
			<emphasis>skeleton</emphasis> following
			<link xlink:href="https://www.unicode.org/reports/tr39/">UTS #39</link>: it decomposes the
			text, replaces each code point with its prototype, and decomposes again. Two strings are
			confusable exactly when their skeletons are equal, which catches spoofing where Cyrillic or
			Greek letters imitate Latin ones.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[// "paypal" with Cyrillic a's looks identical but is a different code-point sequence
Confusables.confusable("paypal", spoofed);   // true
Confusables.skeleton("paypal");              // a matching key, not readable text]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			The skeleton changes length and offsets, so like accent folding it is a derived,
			matching-only form. It is also available as
			<code>ConfusableSkeletonCharSequenceNormalizer</code> and as the
			<code>CONFUSABLE_FOLD</code> term dimension. The mapping comes from the bundled Unicode
			security data file <code>confusables.txt</code>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.language">
		<title>Per-language profiles</title>
		<para>
			<code>NormalizationProfiles</code> selects per-language settings the same way OpenNLP
			already selects a Snowball stemmer by language: ask for a language, or detect it with a
			<code>LanguageDetector</code> when it is unspecified. Each
			<code>NormalizationProfile</code> pairs a language with its Snowball stemmer and the
			diacritic fold appropriate for that language, and builds a search-oriented
			<code>TermAnalyzer</code>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[NormalizationProfile german = NormalizationProfiles.forLanguage("de").orElseThrow();
TermAnalyzer analyzer = german.matchingAnalyzer();   // NFC, case fold, German fold, German stemmer
// "Mueller" and "Müller" both reduce to the same matching term

// detect the language when it is not known
NormalizationProfiles.detect(text, languageDetector).map(NormalizationProfile::matchingAnalyzer);]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			The diacritic fold is the generic accent fold for English and the major Romance languages,
			the German-specific fold (a-umlaut to <code>ae</code>, eszett to <code>ss</code>, following
			DIN 5007-2) for German, and none for the Nordic languages and non-Latin scripts, where
			folding distinct letters is language-wrong. As stated in
			<xref linkend="tools.normalizer.accentfold"/>, this is a search-recall choice, not
			linguistic correctness; a caller that wants different behavior builds a
			<code>TermAnalyzer</code> directly.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.normalizer.reference">
		<title>Reference data</title>
		<para>
			The underlying Unicode data is also available directly as immutable reference tables,
			with O(1) membership tests that match the Unicode standard:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>UnicodeWhitespace</code> lists the 25 characters carrying the
					<code>White_Space</code> property, plus the related look-alike format characters
					(zero width space, byte order mark, ...) that are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
					whitespace. It exposes <code>isWhitespace(int)</code>,
					<code>byCodePoint(int)</code>, and helpers for the line breaks and the
					non-breaking spaces.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<code>UnicodeDash</code> lists every code point carrying the <code>Dash</code>
					property, distinguishing the mathematical minus signs that are excluded from the
					default normalization set.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

</chapter>
