<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
"https://cdn.docbook.org/schema/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<chapter xml:id="tools.spellcheck" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>SpellChecker</title>
	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.overview">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
			The OpenNLP SpellChecker is a native, language-agnostic spelling corrector built on the
			<emphasis>SymSpell</emphasis> (Symmetric Delete) algorithm. Given a (possibly misspelled) term it
			proposes corrections drawn from a frequency dictionary, ranked by edit distance and corpus
			frequency. It can also correct whole phrases, repairing wrongly inserted or omitted spaces
			(word splits and merges) with the help of a bigram language model.
		</para>
		<para>
			SymSpell is fast because it pre-computes a deletes-only index: for every dictionary term it
			derives all strings obtained by deleting up to a small number of symbols and maps each such
			delete back to the originating terms. A query is answered by generating the deletes of the query
			and intersecting them with the index, which turns the costly fuzzy search into a handful of
			hash-map lookups. Candidates are then verified with an edit-distance metric. Because only deletes
			are generated (no insertions, substitutions or transpositions), candidate generation is orders of
			magnitude cheaper than a naïve search over the whole dictionary.
		</para>
		<para>
			The SpellChecker ships as the optional <code>opennlp-spellcheck</code> extension module (package
			root <code>opennlp.spellcheck</code>). It is a good fit when you need to:
			<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
				<listitem>
					<para>clean up noisy user input (search queries, form fields, OCR output) before
						tokenization or classification;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>normalize a training or evaluation corpus as part of a preprocessing pipeline;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>offer interactive "did you mean" suggestions for a single term.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			It is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a grammar checker and it does not require a trained statistical
			model – correction quality is determined entirely by the supplied frequency dictionary.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				The algorithm and its compound-correction heuristic are an independent Java rewrite of the
				SymSpell reference implementation by Wolf Garbe (MIT). Attribution is recorded in the project
				NOTICE file.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.cmdline">
		<title>SpellChecker Tools</title>
		<para>
			The extension provides two command line tools, dispatched through the
			<code>bin/spellcheck</code> launcher of the binary distribution: <code>SpellCheckModelBuilder</code>
			builds a binary model from plain-text frequency dictionaries, and <code>CorrectText</code> corrects
			text using such a model. Each tool prints its usage when invoked with the <code>help</code>
			parameter.
		</para>

		<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.cmdline.build">
			<title>Building a Model</title>
			<para>
				A model is built from a unigram frequency list and, optionally, a bigram list (see
				<xref linkend="tools.spellcheck.dictionary"/> for the file format). Usage of the tool:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ bin/spellcheck SpellCheckModelBuilder help
Usage: opennlp-spellcheck SpellCheckModelBuilder -unigrams in [-bigrams in] -model out \
  [-maxEditDistance num] [-countThreshold num] [-distance damerau-osa|levenshtein] \
  [-corpusWordCount num] -lang lang [-prefixLength num] [-encoding charsetName]

Arguments description:
	-lang lang
		The language tag of the model (e.g. en), stored as model.language.
	-unigrams in
		The unigram frequency dictionary file (word<TAB>count per line).
	-bigrams in
		An optional bigram frequency dictionary file (w1 w2<TAB>count per line).
	-model out
		The output file the binary SymSpell model is written to.
	-maxEditDistance num
		The largest precomputed dictionary edit distance. (default 2)
	-prefixLength num
		Number of leading symbols used for delete generation (must be > maxEditDistance). (default 7)
	-countThreshold num
		Minimum corpus count for a term to be indexed. (default 1)
	-distance damerau-osa|levenshtein
		The edit-distance metric used for verification. (default damerau-osa)
	-corpusWordCount num
		Corpus size N used for compound-correction scoring; 0 (default) derives N from the
		dictionary's summed counts.
	-encoding charsetName
		encoding for reading and writing text, if absent the system default is used.]]>
				</screen>
				The following command builds an English model from a unigram and a bigram dictionary, using the
				default Damerau-OSA edit distance:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ bin/spellcheck SpellCheckModelBuilder -lang en \
  -unigrams en-unigrams.txt -bigrams en-bigrams.txt \
  -model en-spellcheck.bin -encoding UTF-8]]>
				</screen>
			</para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.cmdline.correct">
			<title>Correcting Text</title>
			<para>
				Once a model has been built (or a packaged model is on the classpath), the
				<code>CorrectText</code> tool corrects text line by line. Usage of the tool:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ bin/spellcheck CorrectText help
Usage: opennlp-spellcheck CorrectText [-model model] [-maxEditDistance num] [-lang lang] \
  [-suggest true|false] [-verbosity TOP|CLOSEST|ALL] [-compound true|false] \
  [-inputFile in] [-outputFile out] [-encoding charsetName]

Arguments description:
	-model model
		A binary SymSpell model file. Either -model or -lang must be given.
	-lang lang
		Resolve a packaged spellcheck model for this language from the classpath.
		Either -model or -lang must be given.
	-inputFile in
		The input text file (read line by line). If absent, standard input is used.
	-outputFile out
		The output text file. If absent, standard output is used.
	-compound true|false
		Correct each line as a whole phrase, repairing wrong word splits/merges. (default false)
	-maxEditDistance num
		The maximum edit distance considered per token. (default 2)
	-suggest true|false
		List the suggestions for each token (honoring -verbosity) instead of emitting
		corrected text. (default false)
	-verbosity TOP|CLOSEST|ALL
		How many suggestions to list per token; only used with -suggest true.
		TOP=best only, CLOSEST=all at the smallest distance, ALL=all within -maxEditDistance.
		(default TOP)
	-encoding charsetName
		encoding for reading and writing text, if absent the system default is used.]]>
				</screen>
				By default each line is corrected token by token, reading from standard input and writing to
				standard output:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ echo "the qick brwn fox" | bin/spellcheck CorrectText -model en-spellcheck.bin
the quick brown fox]]>
				</screen>
				With <code>-compound true</code> the whole line is corrected as a phrase, additionally repairing
				wrongly inserted or omitted spaces:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ echo "thequick brownfox" | bin/spellcheck CorrectText -model en-spellcheck.bin -compound true
the quick brown fox]]>
				</screen>
				With <code>-suggest true</code> the tool lists the candidate suggestions for every token
				(honoring <code>-verbosity</code>) instead of emitting corrected text:
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ echo "teh qick" | bin/spellcheck CorrectText -model en-spellcheck.bin -suggest true -verbosity CLOSEST
teh => [the]
qick => [quick, quack]]]>
				</screen>
				Instead of an explicit <code>-model</code> file you can resolve a packaged model from the
				classpath by language with <code>-lang</code> (see
				<xref linkend="tools.spellcheck.models"/>):
				<screen>
<![CDATA[$ bin/spellcheck CorrectText -lang en -inputFile noisy.txt -outputFile clean.txt -encoding UTF-8]]>
				</screen>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.api">
		<title>SpellChecker API</title>
		<para>
			The central abstraction is the <code>SpellChecker</code> interface; its default implementation is
			the <code>SymSpell</code> engine. The interface exposes two ways to correct input:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[public interface SpellChecker {

  // Suggestions for a single term, bounded by maxEditDistance.
  List<SuggestItem> lookup(String term, Verbosity verbosity, int maxEditDistance);

  // Convenience overload: Verbosity.TOP and the configured max edit distance.
  List<SuggestItem> lookup(String term);

  // Corrects a whole phrase, repairing word splits and merges.
  List<SuggestItem> lookupCompound(String input, int maxEditDistance);
}]]>
			</programlisting>
			Each suggestion is an immutable <code>SuggestItem</code> record carrying the corrected term, the
			edit distance to the queried term and the corpus frequency of the suggestion. Its natural ordering
			sorts the best candidate first (ascending edit distance, then descending frequency), so
			<code>get(0)</code> is the top suggestion.
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[public record SuggestItem(String term, int editDistance, long frequency)
    implements Comparable<SuggestItem> { }]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The <code>Verbosity</code> enum controls how many suggestions a <code>lookup</code> call returns:
			<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
				<listitem>
					<para><code>TOP</code> – the single best suggestion (cheapest to compute);</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><code>CLOSEST</code> – all suggestions sharing the smallest edit distance
						found;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><code>ALL</code> – every suggestion within the requested maximum edit
						distance.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			An engine is created from a <code>SymSpellConfig</code> and populated through
			<code>add</code> (unigrams) and <code>addBigram</code> (bigrams). In practice the engine is built
			from a dictionary or loaded from a model (see <xref linkend="tools.spellcheck.dictionary"/>), but
			it can also be filled programmatically:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[SymSpellConfig config = SymSpellConfig.builder()
    .maxDictionaryEditDistance(2)   // largest precomputed edit distance (default 2)
    .prefixLength(7)                // leading symbols used for deletes (default 7)
    .countThreshold(1)              // minimum count to index a term (default 1)
    .editDistance(DamerauOSADistance.INSTANCE) // verification metric (default)
    .build();

SymSpell symSpell = new SymSpell(config);   // or: new SymSpell() for the defaults
symSpell.add("quick", 1_000);
symSpell.add("brown", 800);
symSpell.addBigram("quick", "brown", 120);]]>
			</programlisting>
			Once populated, the engine is safe for concurrent <code>lookup</code> calls. Looking up a single
			term and reading the best suggestion:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[List<SuggestItem> suggestions = symSpell.lookup("qick", Verbosity.CLOSEST, 2);
for (SuggestItem item : suggestions) {
  System.out.printf("%s (distance=%d, frequency=%d)%n",
      item.term(), item.editDistance(), item.frequency());
}]]>
			</programlisting>
			Correcting a whole phrase, including wrongly split or merged words, with
			<code>lookupCompound</code> (which always returns a singleton list holding the best correction):
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[String corrected = symSpell.lookupCompound("thequick brwn fox", 2).get(0).term();
// -> "the quick brown fox"]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.api.distance">
			<title>Choosing an Edit Distance</title>
			<para>
				The verification metric is pluggable behind the <code>EditDistance</code> interface and selected
				through <code>SymSpellConfig</code>. Two implementations are provided:
				<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<code>DamerauOSADistance</code> (the <emphasis>default</emphasis>) – an Optimal
							String Alignment (restricted Damerau-Levenshtein) metric in which a transposition of
							two adjacent symbols counts as a single edit. It is Unicode-aware, operating on code
							points, and matches the variant used by the SymSpell reference implementation. Prefer
							it for natural-language text where transpositions ("teh" → "the") are common
							typos.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<code>LevenshteinDistance</code> – a thin adapter over Apache Commons Text in
							which only insertions, deletions and substitutions count, so a transposition costs two
							edits. It operates on UTF-16 <code>char</code> units. Use it when you want plain
							Levenshtein semantics or to match another system's behavior.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				Both expose a shared, stateless <code>INSTANCE</code> and are passed to the builder:
				<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[SymSpellConfig config = SymSpellConfig.builder()
    .editDistance(LevenshteinDistance.INSTANCE)
    .build();]]>
				</programlisting>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.dictionary">
		<title>Dictionary and Model Format</title>
		<para>
			A SpellChecker is driven by plain-text frequency dictionaries, loaded into an engine by the
			<code>FrequencyDictionaryLoader</code>. Two UTF-8 (by default) line-based formats are supported.
			In both, columns are separated by a single TAB; blank lines, whitespace-only lines and lines
			starting with <code>#</code> (comments) are skipped.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <emphasis>unigram</emphasis> dictionary lists one <code>word&lt;TAB&gt;count</code> per line,
			where <code>count</code> is the term's corpus frequency:
			<screen>
<![CDATA[the	23135851162
of	13151942776
and	12997637966
quick	1885979
brown	1019234
fox	271289]]>
			</screen>
			The optional <emphasis>bigram</emphasis> dictionary lists one
			<code>word1 word2&lt;TAB&gt;count</code> per line (the two words separated by a space, then a TAB
			and the count). Bigrams improve compound correction:
			<screen>
<![CDATA[quick brown	12046
brown fox	5634
the quick	98765]]>
			</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			A model is the built engine together with its source dictionaries and the metadata needed to
			identify it. The <code>SymSpellModels</code> facade builds, serializes and deserializes models, and
			writes the packaged form consumed by the model-resolver. The loaded model exposes a ready-to-query
			engine via <code>getSymSpell()</code>:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[InputStreamFactory unigrams = new MarkableFileInputStreamFactory(new File("en-unigrams.txt"));
InputStreamFactory bigrams = new MarkableFileInputStreamFactory(new File("en-bigrams.txt"));

SymSpellModel model = SymSpellModels.buildModel(
    "en", SymSpellConfig.defaultConfig(), StandardCharsets.UTF_8, unigrams, bigrams);

// Persist the binary model.
try (OutputStream out = Files.newOutputStream(Path.of("en-spellcheck.bin"))) {
  SymSpellModels.serialize(model, out);
}

// Reload it later and query the engine.
try (InputStream in = Files.newInputStream(Path.of("en-spellcheck.bin"))) {
  SymSpellModel loaded = SymSpellModels.deserialize(in);
  SpellChecker checker = loaded.getSymSpell();
  List<SuggestItem> suggestions = checker.lookup("qick");
}]]>
			</programlisting>
			Loading just the dictionaries into an existing engine – for example to add domain terms –
			can be done directly with the loader:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[SymSpell engine = new SymSpell(SymSpellConfig.defaultConfig());
FrequencyDictionaryLoader loader = new FrequencyDictionaryLoader(StandardCharsets.UTF_8);
loader.loadUnigrams(engine, unigrams);
loader.loadBigrams(engine, bigrams);]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.models">
		<title>Multi-language Models</title>
		<para>
			Production multi-language dictionaries are large and are therefore <emphasis>not</emphasis> bundled
			in the <code>opennlp-spellcheck</code> jar. Instead, each language ships as a separate Maven
			artifact named <code>opennlp-models-spellcheck-{lang}</code> (for example
			<code>opennlp-models-spellcheck-en</code>), packaged as a binary model plus a matching
			<code>model.properties</code> descriptor (<code>model.language</code>, <code>model.name</code>,
			<code>model.version</code>, <code>model.sha256</code>).
		</para>
		<para>
			Add the model artifact for the language you need to your classpath:
			<programlisting language="xml">
<![CDATA[<dependency>
    <groupId>org.apache.opennlp</groupId>
    <artifactId>opennlp-models-spellcheck-en</artifactId>
    <version>CURRENT_OPENNLP_VERSION</version>
</dependency>]]>
			</programlisting>
			The <code>SymSpellModelResolver</code> then discovers and loads the matching model using the
			standard OpenNLP model-resolver machinery (see <xref linkend="tools.model"/>). It returns an
			<code>Optional</code> that is empty when no matching model jar is present:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[Optional<SymSpellModel> model = new SymSpellModelResolver().resolveByLanguage("en");
SpellChecker checker = model.orElseThrow().getSymSpell();
List<SuggestItem> suggestions = checker.lookup("qick");]]>
			</programlisting>
			On the command line the same resolution happens when you pass <code>-lang</code> instead of
			<code>-model</code> to <code>CorrectText</code>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.spellcheck.pipeline">
		<title>Pipeline Integration</title>
		<para>
			The SpellChecker integrates into OpenNLP preprocessing through the standard normalizer and stream
			abstractions, so correction can be slotted into an existing chain without bespoke glue code.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>SpellCheckingCharSequenceNormalizer</code> implements
			<code>opennlp.tools.util.normalizer.CharSequenceNormalizer</code> and can be composed with the
			other normalizers (URL, emoji, shrink, ...) inside an <code>AggregateCharSequenceNormalizer</code>.
			It works in one of two modes: <code>Mode.PER_TOKEN</code> (the default) corrects each
			whitespace-delimited token independently and preserves the line's whitespace and punctuation, while
			<code>Mode.COMPOUND</code> corrects the whole input as a phrase, repairing word splits and merges.
			It guards against over-correction (skipping short tokens, numbers and URL/email-like tokens, and
			never changing a word the dictionary already contains) and preserves the original casing pattern of
			each token.
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[SymSpellModel model = SymSpellModels.deserialize(in);

CharSequenceNormalizer normalizer = SpellCheckingCharSequenceNormalizer.builder(model)
    .mode(SpellCheckingCharSequenceNormalizer.Mode.PER_TOKEN)
    .maxEditDistance(2)
    .build();

CharSequence clean = normalizer.normalize("the qick brwn fox"); // -> "the quick brown fox"]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			For stream-based preprocessing two <code>FilterObjectStream&lt;String, String&gt;</code>
			implementations wrap an existing <code>ObjectStream&lt;String&gt;</code> and correct each element as
			it is read:
			<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<code>SpellCorrectingObjectStream</code> corrects each line; in compound mode it may split
						or merge tokens. Use it for free text.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<code>SpellCorrectingTokenStream</code> corrects tokenized data token-by-token and re-joins
						with the same delimiter. It is <emphasis>token-count preserving</emphasis>, so the corrected
						element stays aligned with any parallel annotation (tags, spans).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			Dropping the corrector into a line-based reading chain:
			<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[ObjectStream<String> lines =
    new PlainTextByLineStream(inputStreamFactory, StandardCharsets.UTF_8);
ObjectStream<String> corrected = new SpellCorrectingObjectStream(lines, model);

String line;
while ((line = corrected.read()) != null) {
  // ... consume corrected lines ...
}]]>
			</programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
